All right it's about time to get started thank you everyone for taking the time to
attend the session I...I mean they're not in I
am a program manager working on visual studio today and I'm
going-to be taking you on a tour of some of the new salmon tools we have build and visual
studio twenty fifteen I'm really excited to show what we have today by the way I'd like to extend a
special welcome to everyone that's watching online to channel line welcome to the session as well.
So, today we're going to be doing
a doer of a bunch of new experiences in visual studio and,
in the interest of time I'm going to try to go through this as fast as I can but
I'd really appreciate if you have any questions about anything that we're going to see today
just raise your hand don't need to wait till the very...the presentation feel free to ask the
question I'll make my best...addressing itwe're
going to look at the news animal language service...that we are build and
...twenty fifteen primarily to address a bunch of feedback that we have
heard from you guys we're going to take a tour of the new blend
of build blend from the ground-up to addresssome of the key feedback
vote from you and then I'm going to take you two-a-two
...of my favorite new feature and registry twenty fifteen the ui debugging tools,
for example, I'm going to show you what you can do these tools where we are today and where
...be going forward I'm going to show you some of the profiling tools
in particular we have added a couple of new cool twentytwenty fifteen profiling tools
namely the timeline tool...helps you understand ui responsiveness issues
in your application and then finally I'm going to switch gears a little bit and talk a little bit about
form factor adaptive apps for universal windows platform
maps now the one thing I should make very clear as for most of these demos I'm
going to be doing it in the context of...but
experiences are equally applicable to any example applications you may be building a windows a
...one application...windows...universal
...you'll notice that all of these experiences were pretty consistently across
...labs the only exception is the last one the form factor adaptive apps I'm going to
do a demo in the context of you know,
...universal windows app before I get started I'm just curious what percentage
of how many of you actually build a jpf app today?
Okay, so, that's.
Almost...audience how many of you build a windows a dot one application
okay that's actually pretty good number so that's good to know that, you know, there's an interest that's
...fairly evenly split so I'll that demos that I'm going to show
are primarily jpf but I'll call out any differences that you might want to know when it comes to a windows
...application...windows a dot when application.
So, let's get started the first experience I'm going to demonstrate today is the
news animal editor inverter studio we have actually
rebuilt and from the ground-up using
...platform technologythat we that we affectionately
knew as roslyn because we were to provide a very seamless fully
integrated experience between example and your csharp code we...you know,
everyone should like, you know, the example is just sort of like an extension...you know,
the way you write code and it doesn't make sense to have like a despaired experience we tried to
marry these together and this first...we have added a few new features but the
key here is we have built the foundation to start adding significant new
experience as we evolve you know, future versions of the studio the one thing I should mention
...studios now completely the couple from the designer what really means is
...designer may not work let's say it's writing it's running some of your code and
there's an exception but
...analytical never stop working going forward...be fast and fluid and that's a promise you
...delaware this version of visual studio because...loud and clear you know,
we cannot miss that part up and then finally like I said we want
...the and what we have now is the foundation for experience where you
can start bringing newer new your experiences for editing
example to-you quickly and this is sort of like the first
iteration so let's get started by the way I'm going to primarily do demos so I might,
you know, go a little fast so please,
please...feel free to correct at any point so let me switch do my demo machine?
Which is six all right so
on-screen here I have a simple wpf application it's justan extremely basic
...project management style application but that's besides the point the very first thing you'll
notice as we still have a...designer inverse video and you're doing a lot of work in various
...twenty fifteen to make the
designer more reliable and perform and that's something that we're doing anyway but that said
we fully acknowledge that are a number of you out there that think of visual studio as a coding and
one-minute and want to have the best full-screen coding experience out there so you
guys we are adding a couple of new capabilities to visual studiothat I want
...demonstrate to start with the very first capability inverter studio that you can choose to do if
you're workflow is as such as you can go to the example designer...and you now have
a very clean check box that lets you turn of the designer if that's your workflow?
Whoops I probably should not have twitter running but we'll
...that so let's go...the designer hid okay and it requires the restart
of visual studio...just going to go and do that and,
now you'll notice that when the solution loads back in visual studio it should have
a full-screen you know,
example editor experience that should give you the best possible experience for editing code?
So, that's one part of the workflow but now what have you done on
job to improve your productivity the first feature I want to show you example
...download link allows you to take your content no matter where it's coming from it could be csharp
code...it could be even that will styles and resources that are coming from anywhere
...project we bring that write-in place where you want
edit that provides you with a very seamless editing experience, for example, so,
let's take a log in this particular case I have a window and the window has a
particular code behind...backing it in this case main window let me go
...the main window code historically what I'd have to do is after open
main window example in the solution explore
double-click and then start making changes here but what if I want to make a really quick and it
...my csharp code what's the workflow...twenty fifteen you can just
write click on anywhere in your example...definition and
will bring the csharp code from wherever it is...again editor?
like you would expect all of the editing operations are fully supported here so in this case let me
go...rename this particular class so, I'm going to say rename this to
let's say project tracker main window
...the...you'll notice that...go rename yours, you know,example
as well and everything is very seamlessly integrated...right inside...literature yeah,
just a quick another example of this exact experience let's go and open up yet another
example file in this case it's and even handler that I have here let's say I want to added the even
...code I just...a small tweak to it I can go ahead and say big definition and started in
the even handler from here as well of course the
expectation is that this is great for doing simple things like a week but of course if you...to make, you know,
large-scale...you can just
...that beak window by clicking this guy and then you can start editing your code
...a more full-fledged fashion ok let me show you another experience that we've added
...redistribute twenty fifteen to show that for I mean if you're csharp developer kind of,
you know, there's a bread-and-butter which is the notion of region's if you want to logically think about
your code as organized into different sections...usually, usually go back to your code
an ad...let's go take a look in this case I'm just going to just to show you
the some simple csharp experience first so you can relate to it I can go and type
region say call this is my region as constructors and then
...region here.
But, what so that's, you know, what...and you've been doing all this file but what if you
had to do the same thing example I mean you know, you essentially end up having these really large
example files with a lot of content...sort of logically organize them
so if you don't really care about a particular section of...you can just hide that away and work with
rested example document so...twenty fifteen we have added...to those...
as well to show that an action let's go ahead and bring up intelligence and just
...the word region you'll see that are a couple of new entries for adding regions to...
an added regions and, then give it a names in this case I'm going to call it my tab control
because that's what I really want to sort of isolate out and then I'm going to go to the end of the
dab control and this particular region yet again
I'll just type and region when I do that is emulator now just like my csharp
better lets me collapse of a particular...
Thank you and...database I can continue to focus on the part that I
...now when...designing here's an anecdotal story...designing this feature
we asked our in the pi-zero...guys like this or not actually surprisingly a
lot of people actually don't like it you don't know why I love it but you never go.
But,...if it fits...workflow and your...workflow good and use it you know,
it's it could be useful for some people okay so that's my quick overview of the last
example language service inversely that...a few more small things we have added but, you know,
I'm not in the interest of time going-to skip...those and go to my next section of the demo.
But, before I switch.
I want to detail.
Some back story about
the end blend for video studio has been a cornerstone,
for example, development ever since that came into existence about I'd say
...something like that like about ten years ago over time we have added a
bunch of new capabilities to blend and of course we're studios well but the gap between
lenders studio when it comes to doing certain to activities has, you know,
kind of broadened there are there are things that you just
...you could just do this extra bit and either visual studio and
blend but you can't because that capability doesn't exist you
want to go address that we still believe visual studio is the place where you
...go and energy example code debug your application profiler application that's the best
environment out there but there is the need for home for activities that you typically
associate with you I design and development and we still believe that blends the right place for that we want to
expose capabilities that help you build amazing user experiences so,
in this release we have redesign blend from the ground-up
but, before I talk about that let me just quickly talk about some of the themes of feedback that
...from you guys are users things like example
intelligence ever since the first version of...blend if you think about the trajectory for
...sends it has kinda gone down like to the point where it's barely usable and
...for video studio twenty thirteen it's very common for people to use video studio and
...on different monitors or even on the same monitor and switch back and forth moving
...sort of like change the same file and both the
aidid's move things around it's actually pretty cumbersome you get the series of reload
dialogues and you're kind of confuse and you don't really know why is variously asking means this question
...asking this question that's an experience that's pretty frustrating for
...people out there and then simple lead trivial things like, you know, being able to expand
and collapse nodes in the solution explore are get support registry added get
where what like a year or two ago and...just and doesn't have that
we want to take this released address some of these limitations and make
...such a productive and...that was historically designed to be?
So, we're having to...like
...of esri twenty fifteen which is actually build from the ground-up leveraging a number of
...studio technologieswe wanted to bring sort of like the best of video studio that is
out there and the blind capabilities and marry them together and that's where
you see in the demo today we have worked hard to retain almost all of
the unique capabilities...blend with a few exceptions some of those are still on
...backlog we just haven't been able to get to them in the current
rc that was released on about a couple days ago but the way we think about this
...it's again the start of a journey just like this amr language service have build a foundation
... allowing our team to bring the best
in class design tools to you guys on top of what we are starting here so
that said let's take a tour of the new blind.
here's the project that I was editing let me go and save all these files now historically if you think about
visual studio and being able to interoperate with
...you that one of the ways we floated this was right click on a particulars
ammo file and choose to edit in blend we have brought that capability...now all of
download projects including...so what you can now do is you can write click on any
sample file in this case let me just go and take a look at main window example and we
have a context menu command available called design and blend let's go and open up...
Because I chose to invoked on a particular example file in this case
main window example...try to retain the
...context inside...so it's a fairly seamless shift between
...studio just show you another example let's go back to visual studio and
...click on yet...file let's say dashboard and the design and
...we'll figure out that the solution is already loaded in a
...existing instance of...and then like seamlessly switch over
...file due to sort of open up there so
what's new in blend for redistribute twenty fifteen off the bat and the
monitor probably of the projected probably doesn't make it very obvious you'll notice that we've
introduced a new theme it's actually based on the...studio darting
we're just made a number of tweaks to make a little bit more friendly to people who are you doing you
are development it slightly darker than the...studio team that exists in
...today so if you take a look at tools options you will see that there's a new theme
that's only available online which is the blending in addition to the visual studio teams as well
so if you are work if you think you're a big fan of ...theme of the blue team you can do that as well but
we have added a theme that is unique to blend...cancel out of this dialog and,
walking through the rest of the product we have only brought in features and from various video
...makes sense like...control and projects...solution explorer and things like that we
...brought in tools like unit testing and architecture and all these things because
we're studio still the place you would go to do all of these activities let's take a tour of some of the new
panels inside blend the solution explore is the exact same solution explorer that you'd find in
visual studio and as a result of that all of the feedback
...had the lack of solution folders
are the ability to expand and collapse nodes all of that is now available
...across...video studio in this case let's say I just want to collapse all the nodes I
understood something I mean this is trivial right but people...since two thousand six
...for this feature I mean people have asking where's studio for...many years before...about
that as well so anyways the point is we wanted to bring all of these to the blind customer as well.
The...spain and blend as is the place you would go to create assets and,
add them to your project have retainedthe old experience and not moved over to the
...studio...because the blood experience actually very powerful you can see things like
behaviors which are ways to add no code interactivity to
your application things like stiles that...and various kinds of media like,
for example, in this case...have kept all of the blind capabilities, for example,
you can drag-and-drop images to your design surface and so-and-so forth all of that has been
maintained ...to allow you to sort of like focus on...integration and creation
off good-looking...you know, content and experiences inside bland the
...is very would go to create an added...sm states there's really no change here...
we have been retained exact same functionality and hopefully we'll make it better in the future...the
triggers...rw of developer you kinda know what triggers are you get the same capability in
...for studio twenty fifteen as well and then data...this is where you'd go to create
an...sample data so you can effectively visualizing design and...and make
changes we still have broughtwe have...brought in all of the sample data features
...blend for registry twenty fifteen as well the object and timeline tree of course like...expect is the place where
you'd go and make changes like animations we support that as well so let's go to
create...animation the panel comes up and you can start recording animation so all of
that capabilities I've been reading and in some cases we have made improvements which I'll discuss in a second as
...the properties window I'm not going to talk much about it is just a listing of properties that you can go in edit
the resources spain ...is there as well so you can visualize all of the resources
in your application and make changes to them so in this case I can see all of
the resources that are coming from my app dubs animal and they changes as well as a team
explore there's a place you would go to do your source control and
...related management activities like creating work items and things like that.
So,...said you might have a few questions like,
you know, what are the kinds of things that are different between...of redistribute twenty thirteen and
...fifteen one of the big difference as...spaces then you
...you historically is to have to work spaces one for design and one for animation
well-versed area has an even better workspace management system and...fifteen and we thought
why just not leverage that so what you can do in registry twenty fifteen and you guys probably have seen this and
in a different session is go and create a workspace layouts in this case my
default layout is the one that I use for most activities so I'm just going to...off as default?
But, then I really like my animation view to be like a much broader view than
what's available by default and that constrained three hundred pixel window
...drag-and-drop my object and timeline tree to the bottom of the panel...bottom of
...plan and then go in saved this workspace as a different layouts in this case I'm
going to say let's let me go and say this as my animation layout and once you do that you can
now quickly switch between these two layouts by just going back to the window
menu and seeing those options there so let's say you want to reward back to the default just
...default so on so forth so in some ways just because of the
using registry sl...you get a better workspace management a
set of capabilities in blend as a result of that as well now let's look at some of
...score experiences which comes out comes to editing example let's go
and select a particular element by the way I should say that duals trip which is the way you will
go and create select elements and...design surface so, for example, you want to move
design surface around has been broad closer to the design surface so you don't have to
move your...march if you reach out the controls for selection and things like that let's go and select
...dab control here so in this case I'm going to select
dashboard and my goal is to edit the look and feel of the stab
item which is coming from as a style that is applied that tab...
blends graded styling activities and we continue to bigger that you can write click on
a particular style ...can edits template and we'll sort of bring
...into another noun the unique thing here is the
style is actually coming from a completely different...document right it's coming...example but you
design experience hasn't really changed it's almost as if you...editing main page...animal but
...content is actually coming from...downsample how's that obvious let's bring up the
...editor using...we are able to bring in the style that's existing
in anywhere near...style as and russia reese's or anything
and bring a dryden place so you can edited in the context of the larger
the document that your editing in this case in this case your main windowed on sample?
...experience also allows users to sort of focus on the content that
...editing immediately and not you know, the rest of the
...the rest of example that exists in the document in this case I
want to make a change I want to change the foreground of this tab item so I'm going to
select the value property and I'm going to get the change the
read by the way you get full in dallas...like video studio for all example platforms including
...windows...applications so I'm going to go to make a change...note that as
...as I made the change my design surface updated over here you see
...and, I did it all of that without actually leaving my a
context that I was just editing at and the thing is if you notice
...based on the asterisk on...the
actual edit was committed to a different document submitted possible for-you to seamlessly
an example no matter where it's coming from right in the context of your application
without switching documents and moving things around hopefully...should, you know,
improve productivity of using land as well now.
Let me go and save all these changes let me close let me close these files.
If you I could actually hear you very well
if you don't mind coming to the mike and asking the question I'd really appreciate it thank you and by the way
folks in the webcast can also hear you better if you asked why the mike.
I liked the feature quite well it's pretty cool but doesn't only work...
doesn't work on the property panel as well as the question is cnn writing on the
proper the question is we edited...style in this case coming from
abdullah mammal value and editing your main window does that really work in the properties
of resources as well yes and it does so you should be able to go and
editor brush resource using the resource panel and it should reflect itself in the
designer without you having to switch to am downsample okay thanks no problem thank you so,
let's go out and save all these changes here?
Sorry about that
sable let-me open up my main window back up again to show you the next experience.
Ok, so, now I...along and
...using various studio you go back to visual studio and start making some changes.
Whoops right here so what I want to do isand, this is
the dialogue and we're going to address in a second I won't let's say we want to go and make some changes in this case
I want to change the dialogue application from project tracker to my project tracker
rights I go and make a change now knows notice what happens if I switch back to blend if I want
to do something else you'll get a dialogue that says,
you know, what should I do should I reload all the files...not in...twenty fifteen for both
lenders studio have added the option to reload files automatically
if you haven't really made any changes in either product so you can just
write click on that and say yes to all and we'll just seamlessly reload the changes in
...tointo...in this...in a little bit so you can see what I'm saying the
...has been updated just to prove this one more time that's back go back
to visual studio and make yet another change this case I'm going to type the
word updated save it come back to blend
...seamlessly update without any dialogues are warnings or anything like that?
Thank you now.
One...capability and before we switch gears into some of the other tools that I want
to demonstrate is ui debug is ...accessibility, accessibility
is actually a really important on experience for all of us and you've done a lot of work in
...for...two-twenty fifteen to make the product more accessible so
uses with disabilities can use blend actually can get a lot done pretty much everything and
...accessible to show this point let me actually just move away from using the mouse and
just use the keyboard I can just use control dab switch
over to let's say the resources spain and we bring it back to...to the front and
then you can tab around and start selecting and editing contents in this case I want to navigate the tree
...without using the mouse I can just move things around let's say I want to go rename
a particular resource...just go...key and then I can initiate
the user rename as well even though this is an
access ability feature I know most developers are really, really you know,
keyboard focused and some of the work that...here should help you as well so all of the blind can now be
keep navigated with the keyboard everything is like you expect, you know, fully keyboard accessible?
Ok, thank you yes.
in the states panel for universe...there's the newstate triggers
yet in are those support yet or what is the plan for those, yeah,
so, the question is are state triggers which is a new feature for a windows standing was
...will they be supported are not in today's various
studio twenty fifteen rc build but it will be supported in the final
...training fifteen...so we will allow you to select
states when you make a change...serialized edit
back into the center syntax that they've added in this
ample platform and will also allow you to create adaptive triggers as well as less preview
those on the designer so all of that is coming in the near future just not in today's rc build?
Good question though so ok, let's switch back to.
The slides first second and.
Talk about my favorite feature adversary twenty fifteen ui debugging,
for example, applications we have integrated a live visual tree and a property
explore fully into the debugging experience so you can quickly inspect the visual tree of
your application as your debugging
...you can see the properties for different elements and you can do a lot more that I'll show
wire demos the one thing that's worked reiterating is we see this as a debugging
feature but more importantly the also see this as a foundation for building edit and continue,
for example, we don't want you to restart your debugging session just because
he made a simple example change we want to sort of make it possible that begin pushed edit back-end is
...if you so desire and, sort of get to the point where we can support editing and
continuing example but right now we are is a debugging tool and let me show this an action.
So, let me switch back to.
My display...here.
Show this in the context of the project that we're currently building nowcapabilities available and lenders
enabled but I'm going to do mime demos inverse studio.
Just because the light team is slightly better to
view online so let me go and ...five on this application.
And, start making some changes.
The application launches into the debug are just like you would expect and,
before I talk about the tools themselves a quicknavigation through the application because we're going to be making
some changes to this is a simple dab control like you have dashboard with you know,
it's like a project management style application there's a dashboard with like a map control and
panel for seeing some data the reason I just want to show this is going to fix some of the problems that you're seeing here,
for example, there's nothing showing up in this job down
okay so switch back to visual studio and as soon as you start debugging you will
see a new window that is pinned on the left-hand side called the live visual free if you
...bennett you'll see that it's tracking visual tree of the application
as you're making changes to it so in this case the treat has nine hundred ninety nine
elements by default and that's the case because that's the view of currently you know,
brought up in my application now notice what happens if I change to a different views let's say
...time entry visual see automatically dynamically updates and
shows you the updated visual tree without you having to press the refresh
button in the rare case where the tree gets out of synchronization have given you
the fallback refresh button but we really hope you don't have to ever use it because
it's truly live and tracking all of that it's as you making them in...
What are some of the characteristics of course you would you should be able to select and search for a
particular elements you can just say that control and you should be able to see the
adapt controls in this particular example file on this particular view but,
that's not important enough for this demo let's take a look at a couple of other
capabilities over here on the top left out...live visual tree is a is a
tools for enabling selection in your running application so let's go...turn that
down and go back and interact with application you can no longer interact with application per
say that is you can't drive the application but you can drive selection for the library
in this case let's say I want to select dashboard so that I want to make a change and see how it looks like
...can just click and, will synchronized back into the
...so you can start pushing some changes we also have the capacity to show layout and
earners in your area running applications so let's go and select
that and switch back to the running application you should be able to see things like
...adding and margin communicated via those yellow lines and your normal
alignment communicated by those blue lines so you can diagnose those nasty
issues where your own things don't correctly align and you're trying to figure out what's really happening so on?
And, one final thing before we switch over to
making some changes is this section here for previewing a selection what that really
is selection synchronization these iphones if you if you notice them if you just
also them we're tracking the source, for example, no,
matter where it comes from and that gives us the ability to synchronize when you want to do so,
let's go ahead and write click on let's say the dab control and hit
...will automatically take you to the location in your source code where the type control
...defined so you can start making...animal and, you know,
get them reflected...application but, if you are workflow is such that you want you
want this to happen automatically just make sure you turn on the preview selection and
start looking around so will automatically synchronize in this case I just selected dab item and
we automatically synchronized selection to the tab item my workflow is I want to do it manually
...I...it off but that really depends on you so let me go to internal the
...these options off and then talk about the next experience which is the property
explore...of the properties explorer you can just click the show propertiesbutton over here and
that brings up the properties explorer on the right-hand side now the way we have categorize these
...appear a little confusing up-front but once you understand what's going on I think it's going to
add a lot of value we categorize these properties by the way they
are applied by the running application if,
you know, that...local properties are first applied overridden by
...override properties that are coming from the style that then they override the
...properties are coming from the platform by default that's really
...that's really the vision that we're trying to communicate here with life properties explore
...properties that are local...my element followed by properties that are coming from
the style followed by properties are coming from the system style and
then everything else that's thrown after that now what this allows us to do is if you take a look at
if you expand...of these categories you'll see that some of these properties have a strike through,
through them what really means is just like we have tools and...twelve for
...to help you understand when a properties
set but not getting used that's when the strike through is in this case is
...through because the value send via coercion
...runtime and the values actually coming from really
code in this case we can't really show you the source of that operation but
for places where we can show you the source we will and let's take a look at that demo now that I've selected
the dab item the first thing I want to do is make some changes to it right so let's go to the running,
running application real quick and what...selected here is the stab
items so notice that everything is blue and that's fine let's go and open
the style you'll see that the background is of this particular
...item which is a blue is coming from the style let's go to make a change if I make
it read and switch back to the running application both the dab items we find
out all the styles no matter where they are and we apply the edit to the running application so
...application now reflects the real style that you just changed or
...temporarily changed...to preview how it looks like
against running application so that said how do you send a
property that was never said before so in this case what I want to do is there are two...items both the read
...one red...the green what do I do I like the tab item that I care about in
this case it's already selected and I can just start setting any random properties that I want in this case
...the background property local to the style
...to...the data item just like the background property?
And, make it let's say bing.
You will see that when you did that operation the...the property that came from
the style now is struct through which means is no longer applicable and the property that
ascent locally is the one that's going to win so if I switch back you'll
see that, you know, the one of the dab item styles is now
set dipping whereas the other one and there's only two of them here is said to read because
...coming from the style let's go and make I did this operation I realized that I
made a mistake how do I come out of it you can...reset any property that you want
...case I'm going to go and reset the pink property that I just set and I go back to
the running application
it's all updated and let's say I made a mistake on the entire style and I want to
sort of tested as to how it looks like without the property being set I can even go to a property
...a style and reset as well.
Given a second and then the property should be reset across the application as well so,
we have done a lot of work to push edits that you care about
your quickly test as to what how the application is going to react if you make a small change,
you know, longer have to go to the download make the change run the application realized that
you made a mistake come back...make a change again so on so forth
...really productive for you to sort of quickly push visual tree...running application...
Logging of those changes so the question is there any way to do logging of the
changes the answer is not today but this is where we
are going actually we're going is every time you make the change...to push that back
and do example and then that's your log so you can choose to sort of close all the documents and
say save all unknown save all because I made a mistake or you can choose to sort of like, you know,
specifically save certain files that you care about you have some more advanced capabilities that
we are thinking about it but in this release it's just approach that we making to the running application?
Okay, let me show you a couple more experiences that actually need
...when we talk about debugging your application
...the first thing is...collections like if you think about
jpf or are universe...a lot of things that are that are collections like
...definitions and column definitions and even gradients for a particular brush
resource we have the ability to
...collections in this case I'm going to select this grid and for this grid are actually this
grid and for this...you can see that the road definition...isset locally and it
has a couple of entries associated with it I can go and start making changes to these collections
as well so this case let's go to the second row definition and say my in
let's say my a height is not auto anymore but it's hard coded
to four hundred switch back to the running application and now it's kind of weird but you can see like,
you know, we have enabled you to
...collections as well if I make a mistake and I don't really like what I'm doing I can just type it
back to audio go back to the application and everything is resend back again?
Now one of the things that folks have been asking for
a long-time is debugging data bindings and that's really.
Hard because often something goes wrong you don't get enough information and,
you know, what can you do about it now there are two experiences when we think about data
binding one is like your typical break points experience where you just want to set of break point and break and,
you know, figure out what went wrong that's an experience that we care about we just...the
...twenty fifteen but let me show you another quick way of like hopefully
you debugging a particular data binding in this case I have an issue in my second
dab and, without actually turning off the selection to icon navigate
to the second dab so let me go and turn off the selection do and navigate ...second
tab and application...a couple of combo boxes that don't have any entries
and them and I'm wondering why that's the case how
...this issue one option would be you select the combo box?
And, say hey...exactly this combo box coming from this actually pretty hard if you don't actually on
...animal so, the selection do is actually useful just to get there but,
you can then go to the combo box itself and view the source.
And, you can't you can see in this case, you know,
it's an obvious mistake to a binding but let's say...was not as obvious how
...debug this issue one way of doing this would be just look at the data context and figure out where the
data context is coming from in the visual tree and then figure out where you're binding
...sort of breaking...search for the data context property.
We allow you to sort of explore search for it but at the same time in this case you can see
that is said to my view model but you can also expanded and look at all of the
properties and values that it's coming from in this case I know that ours is
observable collection and expanded and all of the values are there as well so I know that, you know,
the data model itself is correct I just did a mistake in my binding that way you can sort
of just by traversing the visual tree and taking a look at the data context you
can fairly effectively diagonal certain class of binding issues I'm not saying
that's equality putting a break point I think there is value in both propositions this is one of
experiences that we are the that we want to delaware...twenty fifteen.
So, that's my click dude...ui debugging tools,
for example, any specific questions so far before I switch gears.
Okay, so, let me switch back to slides for a second.
Like I said, you know, the big things we want to do going forward is pushing the edge that you just
made bacterias animal that's a feature that you really want to do and then eventually like build some
more richer visualizations for debugging data bindings and things like that.
Let's switch gears to profiling tools
...fifteen we have introduces the field new profiling tools in particular the
timeline tool that allows you to understand ui responsiveness issues
...my application not really starting up fast wire their issues...working with
application have a network tool that allows you to monitor network requests and things like that we
do support vpf and windows universal...with all of these tools but,
today I'm going to demo in the context of vpf they
do work for all scenarios and the other thing to notice these tools only work if you're running on windows
...today but we are working for inversely twenty fifteen they will also work if you're running on
windows seven so that's really not an issue is just a point in time thing
what are these tools capable off let's go and take a quick look at those.
Let me close the solution and open up yet another solution that helps me diagnose show
...performance issue diagonals and fix it in this case
I have a simple stockcar application let me go and run it the first thing you'll notice
is when the app starts up it takes some time it takes about five to seven seconds
...let's just let me just give it about five seconds so five seconds later the abstracts
and that's not good because you're...and...very happy so let's go and take a look at
what went wrong in terms of...and wide slow.
In registry twenty fifteen you can also run profiling tools just like you'd
expect you can in this case I'm going to select the cpu usage
...which is,
you know, one potential reason why map could be slow but I'm going to select this new
tool that we've introduced which is the timeline...this allows you to visualize what's really happening
...by the way this is a...application that I'm demonstrating?
So, let's go ahead yes and start you know,
a profiling session I don't really have to do anything we are visual
...collecting all the dw data and, it's should just take a second and,
let me go...stop the collection give it a couple seconds
...analyze all that...w data aggregated and presented in the form of...report that
...can act on.
So, once that's happened you'll get a report with
a graph that sort of gives you a high-level overview of what really as happened all these blue
bars over here some sort of parsing is happening you're trying to create some sort
of example element and that's taking a bunch of time all these orange
bars over here some significant layout operation is happening as you can see that application
...a lot of elements and hence you should expect quite a bit of layout to happen in that case now
...twenty fifteen
we have added notion of grouping certain kinds of logical...that
makes sense to you so in this case we have logical group of events that the bucket together
application startup and that's really the problem I'm trying to diagnose at this point
why is my application not starting up quickly I can is right click on
and evened and say I want to investigate this event and I don't really care about anything else I can
...what...now done...captured all of the evens that only correspond
...contributed...delay and group them together to show them under application
startup and now I can start looking at and issues there is some garbage collection happening but that's
not really significant majority of the work seems to be still happening in parsing main window
I can expanded I can see exactly what happened...some of the
...main window but really like the problem is once when I look at all of this code I kinda know
that applications database slow and it's constructing main window that's causing
...but what do I do next that's where
...profile languages the which is the ability to run to tools together could
come to help in this case I'm going to switch over to the cpu usage tool and I'm
going to look at what exactly happened when I look at my cpu usage let's go and
...plate and say in this case I know that fifty-seven person...the dime has been
send in spend and this one function I can keep drilling down to say okay
where is that most of the work is
happening again to this point where that's my code and beyond out as platform
...it's the get data function that's doing something that's going to take a look at what's
happening I can just like you...and start inspecting as to what my
...is doing in this case just because I...my code and fetching data synchronous
...and that's causing my ui to pause the fixes pretty simple just do
a task dot run when I'm calling that particular function rapid in.
Anonymous delegate here.
that's pretty much it...to do to fix this particular function have zeroed in on the problem in this case it's
a fairly simple issue...zeroed in the problem of fixed...and now when I run
...nap should hopefully if everything works startup faster and everything should get
...are like populated asynchronous...as well as you know,...a today on synchronous
...on the right thread let me actually switch gears to show the memory profiler for a second.
go back to my old project tracking application and there is a memorization this application
it's using a lot of memory how do I know what's going on you can again use the profiling tools
inverse studio and you can you can turn on the memory usage tool
...usage tool by the way one of the unique capabilities as a helps you
track both native and manage...case your application as...a lot of
native memory allocations going on you can choose to do that as well but in this case it's appear
managed application and I don't really have to worry about native code so let's go and start profiling.
And, what you can do is the way you do memory profiling usually is you would
take a snapshot before your operation that you just did wait for a second for that
snapshot to complete now do your memory intensive operation in this case might when I
...like my time entry and I select my report
view it's actually causing a bunch of allocations...the snapshot and starred
differing the due to figure out what extra objects...created why they were created so on so forth so,
let me stop the profiling session and lead
give registry a second to analyze the data and take a look at what exactly went wrong?
Just one second hopefully should come through there we go
and you can see like between these two snapshots there was a growth of about three
md the question is why and that's the question you're trying to answer and a bunch of objects
...allocated as...registration give you a detailed report of what objects
...created who's holding onto those objects and things like that in this case
...new data grades were created and they sort of if you look at if you
expand these they together almost out up to like three md so that's where most of
your allocations is coming from using things like what they are referencing
and things like that you can narrow down to the actual root cause of who's doing
the instantiation and then go and fix the problem using the memory tools and...studio.
I'm going to switch gears to show my last experience any question about the profiling tools.
...the question is what versions averse studio have this experience the memory tool is available
...to your twenty thirteen but, it only works
on windows a dot one right now the memory and timeline tools are both available in
...studio twenty fifteen and they should by the time you're done work on windows seven or
higher.
Okay.
Since we're running out of time I'm going to be able to do just one of the three experience
I want to do all three this is an experience that is very specific to windows universal windows
apps and that's about how do you do adaptive ui which is how do you sort of make
...great when it's running on a bunch of, you know,
...I'm out there
...multitude of approaches that you can take all the way from controls that just do,
you know, smart things you don't really have to do anything just make sure that you using the right controls and they will do the right
thing for you can like the gentleman was asking you can use state triggers so you can you can switch to a
visual state that's all fine but what if you really wanted to do like a completely tailored
view for a device right what if...xbox you I was so different than your phone ui
...a desktop ui that you really
wanted to do something different that's the experience what I'm going to show because the other two were already covered in some
of the sessions and in particular there is some really interesting developer tricks that you can do for this
last experience let me show that an action by opening
up universal windows application I'm going to run this application first ad design
...application to run on my mobile device and let me go and run it.
When I run this application...feel about this bill quality good question
let me go and select ...category and look at certain appetizers you'll see that the
view looks great?
Oebps.
Great question sorry about that.
Terrago sorry.
The application looks great like you can just navigate around and,
the ux is actually fairly optimized for the mobile device.
Now I'm ready to bring desktop into the makes and I want to run this application on my machine right let's go
and run this app.
And, see how it looks like on my own machine.
...simulator if I so...given a second.
The app boots up you can select a particular appetizer you can...you know,
something out there but see the
...doesn't really low-grade because it's optimized for mobile and I'm really running it
...full-screen desktop mode in this particular scenario so we're going
to do about it the reason I'm showing this experiences inversely twenty fifteen
...doing bunch of work so you can share code across mammal files as well and,
the way you do that is to just...view to your application let's go and do that let's go and
create a new folder in this case I'm going to call itdevice family?
Does desktop and I'm going to go out and add a new example view to
it in this case I can just do and add new item and because ample view and type of whole bunch of
...that optimizes for that user experience but I'm going to do that because that's going to take a bunch of time let
me just go and add...existing file that I already created before and I'll open
...showed what it is just as...file with the user experience that's optimize for you know,
the desktop form factor nothing really fancy but the thing to note here is
it does not have a code behind that is if you look at the x...class
it doesn't have any code behind it that's because all of the code is shared with
the generate file that already exists in which case it is recipe instructions
...seos...you...to do is to give multiples
...the same code behind so you can reuse code across these
...files and do everything else like you're even handlers are shared on your everything
else shared except your examples different right what does that mean for us...I build and run?
That's going to build and run
this application and take a look at how it looks like?
Hopefully should fix the problem.
Now if I go
and select my appetizer an ice like this thing it looks pretty.
Good I guess so, we've done a lot of work to tailor this particular view now you could have done this using any
other techniques as well that's really up to you but
...dramatically different user experiences this is one of the techniques that you can consider to make sure
that your app looks great on certain form factors one thing I wanted to talk about this particular
experience let me go and are you guys know what initialize component is which is the way
we load this animal but one thing about universal windows
...I go to the do go to my initialize component we now have
...override for the initialize component very can bastion any example uri and
we load that uri as a part of part of the part of the instantiation of
the control so you could write some really complex business logic that sort of calculates
what's that what's the best possible ui that can potentially so
your customer and then just call into initialize component that
...loaded and displayed this allows you to create are really tailored user
experiences for your customers for the form factors that you care about most?
So, let's quickly switch back to slides and.
Summarize so we have seen a number of new experiences...twenty fifteen, for example,
tools and, you know, you can get a little bit more of the details on various sessions and things like
that in particular I mean now it's kind of like you know, you can go to msdn and view these if you have missed some of
the sessions there are a couple of sessions that are specifically dedicated to creating great-great
user experiences that will great across devices I just want to show
one technique because that's primarily a code reuse technique more than anything else but,
you can use a number of these techniques to build a great user experiences
please don't forget to complete evaluation form for some reason I don't have that you know,
barcode scanner thingy but I'd really appreciate...help us improve
and bring better content you in the future and...saidopen up the question
...any questions thanks-a-lot for taking the time to attend I really appreciate.
...for the lives animal editing is it a compatible with
like windows phone is like the simulator can devices doo-doo,...
so, the question is my you call it the ui debugging to,
for example, but, I get reducing is the united are the ui debugging tools,
for example, compatible with devices and absolutelyno,
matter where your app is running...could be an xbox that could be windows phone
we should be able to lead to select and edited and push standards as well...like thank you.
For the tailored view this switching that was happening there
was that automatic based on...the solder name,
yeah, so, the question I'll just...be a just in case
... mike is actually...is the is the is the feature for tailored views
the switching happen automatically in this particular case yes because
...basically using the resource manager and windows
direct load the right resource but like the reason I wanted to show this experience particularly
is because you have full control over that you ideal in the most
...you should not just depend on the name of the device family because it's
sometimes hard to make that distinction if you want to do it that's fine but you can also choose to sort of like
...custom code and figure out what's the best possible view and call
...initialize component that particulars
...load the view but yes the answer short answer is yes okay,
yeah, it's you sort...some similarities to wpf themes...like they're, they're
...names that match-up with exactly what device family that's...specific, you know,
exactly thank you.
That's ...the
profiler actually available as a service.
Is the profiler available as a service
my by this question I'm guessing you're asking can you run it from a command-line or something like that
...if...my applet someplace else that I...to profile it like we don't
supposed so the question is if it's a remote scenario can be profiler don't supports today
...don't support launching app remotely for profiling that's something that we want to address
in the future but today task to be run locally
...you can run it on the device and you can profile against it but you can run it across using
...ip address or something like that and then profile and there you can certainly do it for devices that
...connective dresser for the live properties if
you examine the data context is that cause lazy loader properties again on lazy
loaded like to get their value that's a good question so the...
I actually...math.
I would say we don't do anything specific but because we are querying the
data context property
whether something special happens that's a good question we don't do anything...
we just query...runtime for the data context show it and, do
it but as a part of the...if you do something smarter?
Then, yeah, that dial execute as well.
Thank you yes...easily needs...support the and,
you...with...forms I'm...ortiz something out of the question
the question is do we want to support examine from something that's an example...informs.
The...have been built with an architecture that's very agnostic and we can plug-in anything
in our first iteration...still be optimize for windows client applications
but that's...that's something that, you know, is interesting to us as well thank you very much no problem?
Will there be a blend version for universal...
Malaria blend version for universe...actually lenders therefore all example platforms there is no,
such thing as...for universe
...if you if you get visual studio twenty fifteen community which is our free edition you'll get
blend and...support for all kinds of...including windows universe...
Any other questions.
Okay, all right thanks everyone I'm happy to answer your question zero as well.